<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Frozennotes</title>
    <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages" />
    <updated>2023-06-01T12:51:07-07:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>jesse martin</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages</id>

    <entry>
        <title>TEA FOR SLEEPLESSNESS AND INSOMNIA</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/tea-for-sleeplessness-and-insomnia.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/tea-for-sleeplessness-and-insomnia.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/22/th-3717326204" medium="image" />
            <category term="tea"/>

        <updated>2023-06-01T12:51:07-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/22/th-3717326204" alt="" />
                    If you are one of the many people that suffer from sleepless nights or poor quality sleep then you will be all too familiar with the effects. Getting an insufficient amount of sleep or poor quality if sleep can have a devastating impact on your&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/22/th-3717326204" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <header class="entry-header">
<p class="entry-title"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">If you are one of the many people that suffer from sleepless nights or poor quality sleep then you will be all too familiar with the effects. </span><strong style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit;">Getting an insufficient amount of sleep or poor quality if sleep can have a devastating impact on your life.</strong><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> It can affect your work, your studies and your relationship</span></p>
</header>
<div class="entry-content">
<p>In the long term, insomnia does not damage your emotional state and your daily life, <strong>it can also have a devastating effect on your physical health.</strong></p>
<p><strong>Certain lifestyle changes can help matters.</strong> Bedtime routines, exercise and relaxation exercises can all help but for many people, they are at the end of their wits. As somebody who has experienced insomnia at various stages of my life, I know just how difficult it can be. There is nothing worse that in lying in bed watching the hours go by and the light starting to come through. <strong>The more you worry about getting to sleep, the less it is likely to happen.</strong></p>
<p>If you are in a similar boat, then I am sure you have tried all sorts of solutions to your problem and you may have given herbal medications a go. Maybe they did not have the desired effect and you are looking to try an alternative solution.</p>
<p><strong>This article will take a look at some of the best herbal teas to remedy your sleeplessness</strong>. Some like chamomile are very well known and popular choices. Others may be completely new to you and you might like to give them a try.</p>
<div class="code-block code-block-22">
<div id="amzn-assoc-ad-d5eeca80-24af-40d4-8736-1f850df9ce2f"></div>
</div>
<p><strong>If one type of tea does not work for you, try not to despair; it is quite possible that another tea will have the effect you are looking for.</strong> They are certainly worth trying and hopefully with a little trial and error, you will hit in the best tea to remedy your condition.</p>
<h2>CAN TEA REALLY HELP YOU TO SLEEP BETTER?</h2>
<p>There really is not a great deal of scientific evidence relating to the subject but many people swear by the soothing and calming properties of their favorite herbal teas. Let us look at it this way…. <strong>if you enjoy a warm drink before bed time and it helps you to relax then regardless of scientific evidence, that is the most important thing.</strong></p>
<p>While research suggests that herbal teas lack the sedative qualities that you may be looking for, the fact that you can enjoy a nice warm a drink before bed is actually relaxing in and of itself. <strong>For some people, just the process of adding a nice soothing cup of tasty herbal tea into their night time routine can have a profound effect on their quality of sleep.</strong></p>
<h2>THE BEST TEAS TO HELP YOU SLEEP</h2>
<h3>1) CHAMOMILE TEA</h3>
<p><strong>Chamomile tea is probably the best known of all the herbal teas when it comes to promoting a good night’s sleep.</strong> It is one that I can personally vouch for along with the millions of other people who have found it to be effective.</p>
<p>There is no hard evidence that chamomile tea has any especially powerful sedative qualities but people the world over continue to use it and swear by its effect. <strong>It is found as an ingredient in many bedtime tea brands and is easy to make yourself by drying the flowers and then brewing them.</strong></p>
<p>I find chamomile tea absolutely delicious in its own right but some people including my wife prefer to sweeten it with honey.</p>
<h3>2) VALERIAN ROOT TEA</h3>
<p>Unlike most other teas used for promoting sleep, valerian can actually boast a certain amount of scientific evidence. <strong>Studies have demonstrated that valerian root has sedative properties which can calm the mind and ease stress and anxiety.</strong></p>
<p>Valerian tea is made from the flower’s roots and it has been used for many years to help people deal with stress, anxiety and insomnia. <strong>You may need to use valerian tea each night for a number of weeks before you start feeling its full sedative effects</strong> but for anybody with insomnia, valerian tea may well have the answers.</p>
<h3>3) LAVENDER TEA</h3>
<p>Lavender essential oil is very well-known for its abilities to calm the mind and improve both the duration and the quality of sleep. <strong>A number of studies into the effects of lavender have revealed it can help ease anxiety, reduce heart rate and help people to relax.</strong></p>
<p>When you drink lavender tea, you are getting the benefits of both the fragrance and the plant’s volatile oils. It is very easy to make yourself from the fresh or dried lavender buds.</p>
<div> </div>
<div><span style="color: var(--headings-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.42383em; font-weight: var(--font-weight-bold); letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">4) ST. JOHN’S WORT TEA</span></div>
<p>Most commonly used and best-known for its natural ability to treat depression, <strong>St John’s wart can also help treat anxiety</strong>. Because anxiety and stress are very common reasons for sleep troubles and insomnia, it makes sense that it could help calm the mind and promote better sleep. <strong>It may work by stimulating the GABA receptors which are involved in releasing the chemicals responsible for sleep.</strong></p>
<h3>5) GINGER AND TURMERIC TEA</h3>
<p><strong>This is an extremely healthy blend of two of the healthiest known herbs and spices.</strong> If you love the taste of ginger as much as I do, then you will certainly enjoy a relaxing healthy cup of ginger tea spiced up with the incredibly therapeutic turmeric.</p>
<p>Even if it does not help you get off to sleep, <strong>you will benefit a great deal from the health properties of this tea.</strong> Add some good quality honey to taste if you find the flavor too pungent.</p>
<h3>6) LEMON BALM TEA</h3>
<p><strong>Lemon balm is considered to be a calming herb and is known for its sedative qualities.</strong> Although the effectiveness of lemon balm as a sedative is still in dispute, there is some evidence that when combined with valerian root, it can help people to get a better night of sleep. Lemon balm tea may also help you deal with the anxiety that is preventing you from getting off to sleep.</p>
<h3>7) PEPPERMINT TEA</h3>
<p>Peppermint tea seems like a strange addition to the list at first glance because it is often linked with boosting energy. However, peppermint and peppermint tea are also well-known for their ability to calm the stomach and improve digestion.</p>
<p><strong>If your sleeplessness is causes by indigestion, then this is the perfect antidote for you</strong>. Try drinking a cup after a heavy meal in the evening and we are sure you will notice the difference.</p>
<h3>8) MAGNOLIA BARK TEA</h3>
<p>This is a less common tea in the West but Magnolia bark is a <strong>common remedy for anxiety and other emotional issues in parts of Asia.</strong> Because of its ability to relieve anxiety and calm the mind, many people have found it to be a great natural sleep aid.</p>
<h3>9) PASSION FLOWER TEA</h3>
<p><strong>Passion flower supplements are often used to help relieve stress, anxiety and other nervous disorders.</strong> Many people also find it to be the perfect remedy for mild insomnia. Passionflower might work by stimulating the production of the chemicals needed for sleep. One study has found that drinking passionflower tea helped the participants enjoy a better quality of sleep through the night.</p>
<h3>10) LINDEN LEAF TEA</h3>
<p>Linden leaf is best known for its ability to relieve colds and flu but it also has a reputation for calming the nerves. It crops up on many people’s recommended lists of teas to drink before bed and it may have mild sedative qualities.</p>
<h3>SLEEP TEA RECIPE</h3>
<p>You can try any of the teas mentioned above and hopefully one or more will prove effective. For a tea lover like me, I enjoy creating my own blends and you may like to try this simple recipe. <strong>It is full of some of the best natural sleep herbs and should hopefully help you achieve a good night of sleep.</strong></p>
<h4>WHAT YOU WILL NEED</h4>
<ul>
<li>Two tablespoons dried chamomile</li>
<li>1 tablespoon each of peppermint, dried passionflower, lemon balm and valerian</li>
<li>Honey to taste</li>
</ul>
<h4>WHAT YOU NEED TO DO</h4>
<ul>
<li>Combine your herbs in a bow and store them in a container in a cool place.</li>
<li>Use 2 teaspoons of your herbs to each 2 cups of boiling water.</li>
<li>Steep for between 5 and 10 minutes according to taste.</li>
<li>Strain then sweeten with your honey of you so choose.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are plenty of choices for those of you who would like to try a natural sleep remedy. <strong>Which tea do you find the best sleep aid of them all?</strong></p>
<p>If we have missed any off the list, please let us know and we can add it.</p>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>5 Tips and Steps for Brewing Best Coffee</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/5-tips-and-steps-for-brewing-best-coffee.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/5-tips-and-steps-for-brewing-best-coffee.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/21/Brew-at-Home-Trees-Organic-VAN_5151r-1024x842.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="coffee"/>

        <updated>2023-05-31T12:50:20-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/21/Brew-at-Home-Trees-Organic-VAN_5151r-1024x842.jpg" alt="" />
                    When customers purchase our organic coffee beans for home brewing, the question most frequently asked is about how to make the best cup of coffee. Well, it’s a big question. Therefore, we’ve assembled 5 tips and steps for optimal brewing at home and for improving&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/21/Brew-at-Home-Trees-Organic-VAN_5151r-1024x842.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <header class="entry-header "></header>
<div class="entry-content clear">
<p><a href="https://treescoffee.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/Brew-at-Home-Trees-Organic-VAN_5151r.jpg"></a>When customers purchase our organic coffee beans for home brewing, the question most frequently asked is about how to make the best cup of coffee. Well, it’s a big question. Therefore, we’ve assembled 5 tips and steps for optimal brewing at home and for improving the flavour qualities of your organic coffee experience!<span id="more-5573"></span></p>
<p>The jury is still out on the best brewing technique for extracting that heavenly cuppa java. But, it’s safe to say that manual brewing methods provide more quality control of the process; hence, a more flavourful coffee. Still, there is great debate about the best manual method to extract coffee, ranging from pour-over/drip, press, vacuum, pressure to percolate. Not to mention there’s a plethora of simple to sleek brewer devices. But one thing is certain; the material on selecting the most suitable method and equipment is endless. Whether you’re a coffee connoisseur or a regular joe, the method will depend on individual taste and level of convenience. While we support all coffee brewing methods, our focus on this occasion is the popular French press method and its finer points for brewing at home, that is practical, convenient and straightforward!</p>
<h2>The Buzz on French Press Brewing</h2>
<p>The French press (also known as a Cafetiere, coffee press, press pot or Melior) is widely considered the best method for brewing delicious coffee at home, especially with premium beans. The French press method extracts, arguably, more superior flavours than any other method. It is well suited for coffee drinkers that enjoy a luscious, expressive and complex taste experience. They are treated to rich, refined and robust but smooth flavours, with heavier body and stronger aroma. Pressed coffee also serves up more caffeine . And, just as important for people on-the-go, French press coffee is simple and fast to make/clean up!</p>
<p>We think the purest coffee flavours can be drawn and kept through the French press. Master tasters think so too, as they claim the taste experience from a press method is closest to that from coffee cupping. French press coffee is basically unfiltered, unlike pour-over/drip techniques with paper filters. In a press pot, ground coffee is soaked, steeped and strained in hot water; therefore, coffee’s flavourful essential oils, caffeine and antioxidants are better diffused and preserved.</p>
<p>Although the French press is an easy-to-use design, there’s more to making good coffee than adding ground beans, pouring hot water, waiting, and pressing. The other appeal of the French press is the ability to control the quality of a cup of coffee. Therefore, here are 5 simple tips and steps for brewing the tastiest hot coffee with your French Press.</p>
<h2>#1 Great Coffee Starts with Great Organic Beans</h2>
<p>Use whole beans! Organic coffee taste better and is a healthier choice as organic beans are free of chemical pesticides and fertilizers. Try single origin beans to fully appreciate the true coffee profile of a particular country.<a href="https://treescoffee.com/products/coffee/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"></a></p>
<p>Use fresh beans! To maintain the freshness of roasted coffee, buy small quantities regularly. For example, get enough for a week, or maybe two, at a time. The rule of thumb is that roasted coffee can go stale 15 days after roasting. Our goal is to provide freshly roasted coffee, which is why we roast our coffee beans in small batches daily.</p>
<ul>
<li>Store your whole coffee beans in a clean, opaque, air tight sealed container (eg. Airscape canister*).</li>
<li>Place the container in a cool and dark area of your kitchen (eg pantry), not in the fridge/freezer.</li>
</ul>
<h2>#2 Size Matters – Get the Right Grind</h2>
<p>Grind your whole organic coffee beans just before brewing. A coarse grind (eg. size of breadcrumbs, sea salt or steel cut oats) is preferred for French Press coffee. Use a burr grinder, or for more precision use a grinder with automatic settings (eg Breville Smart Grinder with pre-sets for French press and the number of cups*).</p>
<ul>
<li>To make 1 cup in a 12 oz press pot, grind to make 2-2.5 tbsp (~14g) of coffee</li>
<li>To make 8 cups in a large 34 oz press pot, grind to make 8-10 tbsp (~58gr) of coffee</li>
</ul>
<h2>#3 Not all French Presses are Created Equal</h2>
<p>When you buy a French press, examine the quality of the mesh or strainer (mostly stainless steel) on the bottom of the plunger. As the mesh is not as fine as a paper filter, a small amount of coffee fines or residue can settle on the bottom of the cup. Most people don’t mind the sediments on the bottom and leave the last sip in the cup; however, a better quality French press and mesh can minimize the amount deposited. For example, the stainless steel, double walled Bodum Columbia has a fine silicone mesh and seal on its plunger, reducing residue in a cup of coffee*.</p>
<p>Add coarsely ground organic coffee to the bottom of your chosen French Press container.</p>
<ul>
<li>Warm up the empty French press with a hot water rinse before adding ground coffee.</li>
</ul>
<h2>#4 Water Temperature is Important</h2>
<p>Hot water is needed to draw out the flavours of coffee beans, but it’s the temperature that allows the correct balance of extraction. Hot water for coffee brewing should be between 195 – 205F. Water boils at 212 F; hence, allow boiled water to sit off the heat for about 30 sec. before adding it to the coffee grounds, or consider using a thermometer to measure the temperature. Some electric kettles have variable temperature controls (eg. Breville IQ Kettle has a French Press 200F setting*).</p>
<p>Pour just-off-boiled water onto the coffee grounds in the pre-warmed press pot, being sure all grounds are saturated (most of the grounds have floated to the top). Allow the coffee to ‘bloom’. Do not put the plunger lid on top.</p>
<ul>
<li>Filtered water is better, particularly if tap water has a strong chlorine smell and taste.</li>
<li>Boil the amount of water that you need to avoid waiting for a long time</li>
<li>For 1 cup of coffee in a small 12 oz press pot, use 8-10 oz of water</li>
<li>For 8 cups of coffee in a large 34 oz press pot, use 24 – 30 oz of water</li>
<li>Generally, use two tablespoons of ground coffee for each six ounces of hot water</li>
</ul>
<h2>#5 Steep It. Press It!</h2>
<p>Set up a time to count down from 4 minutes. Start it once the hot water is poured into the French press pot. After 1 minute, stir the water with coffee gently and thoroughly. Be careful using a metal spoon in a glass French press, or consider using a wooden spoon. Put the plunger with lid on top of the pot making sure the plunger is in the up position and mesh or strainer is above the water’s surface. Let it stand and wait.</p>
<p>When the 4-minute timer is complete for this slow and gradual brew, press the plunger down gently while pushing the grounds to the bottom.</p>
<p>Your delicious home brewed coffee is ready to serve! If you’re using a larger French press pot and drinking one cup at a time, consider pouring all the coffee into a thermal carafe to avoid a bitter taste due to over extraction in the French press.</p>
<p>The above 5 tips and steps serve as a good starting point for improving your home brewed hot coffee when using the manual French press process. We recommend you test and adjust all the above variables to suit your palate. As the saying goes, ‘life is too short for bad coffee’, so enjoy brewing and sipping great organic coffee!</p>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Popular Methods for Brewing Coffee at Home</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/popular-methods-for-brewing-coffee-at-home.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/popular-methods-for-brewing-coffee-at-home.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/20/Manual-Coffee-Brewing-Methods-768x432.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="coffee"/>

        <updated>2023-05-31T12:43:44-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/20/Manual-Coffee-Brewing-Methods-768x432.jpg" alt="" />
                    For coffee enthusiasts who want to brew a better cup of java at home with our organic coffee beans, here are six popular manual coffee brewing methods to consider using, beyond the household automatic coffee maker. Your preferred method will boil down to your personal&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/20/Manual-Coffee-Brewing-Methods-768x432.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <article id="post-6237" class="post-6237 post type-post status-publish format-standard has-post-thumbnail hentry category-coffee-tea-drinks tag-coffee-brewing tag-coffee-tips tag-home-coffee-brewing ast-article-single">
<div class="ast-post-format- single-layout-1 ast-no-date-box"><header class="entry-header ">
<div class="entry-meta"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">For coffee enthusiasts who want to brew a better cup of java at home with our organic coffee beans, here are six popular manual coffee brewing methods to consider using, beyond the household automatic coffee maker. Your preferred method will boil down to your personal taste, time and technique!</span></div>
</header>
<div class="entry-content clear">
<p><span id="more-6237"></span></p>
<p>There is a wide acceptance that manual brewing methods allow for better quality control and a superior coffee experience. For many, it’s more fun and fascinating to have a hands-on approach with their brewing process rather than hitting a ‘brew’ button on a machine. The growing trend or movement for gourmet-type coffee making has resulted in a staggering range of gadgets and differing opinions. While we support all styles of coffee brewing, our focus this time will be to touch on six of the more crowd-pleasing manual coffee making options that could complement our single origin, organic coffee beans, available at any of our coffeehouse locations.</p>
<h2>A Quick Guide to Manual Coffee Making Styles</h2>
<p>Below is a brief overview of six manual coffee making styles, including some quick tips, as a starting point to help you select your preferred method of infusion, from pour over/drip, plunger/pressed, percolate to vacuum.</p>
<h3><strong>Pour Over/Drip: Coffee Cone</strong></h3>
<p>One of the oldest, simplest, fastest and cheapest ways to brew coffee is the drip method using a coffee cone and paper filter. Hot water is poured evenly over coffee grounds in a paper filter. With gravity, the brewed coffee drips slowly and directly into a cup or pot. Coffee cones are made of plastic, glass, stainless steel or ceramic. The shape of the cone and their filters will influence the flavours. Popular brands include Melitta, Hario V60, Kalita Wave and Bee House.</p>
<ul>
<li>Grind of Beans: medium-fine to coarse</li>
<li>Quantity of Coffee: 3 tablespoons of coffee (21g)</li>
<li>Brewing Time: 1-3 minutes</li>
<li>Flavour Profile: Smooth, round body</li>
<li>Cost: $8-$71 (extra cost for filters)</li>
<li>Produces a single cup of coffee</li>
<li>Easy to clean</li>
<li>Portable</li>
<li>Requires paper filters that match the cone</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Pour Over/Drip: Chemex</strong></h3>
<p>Chemex is a beautifully designed and elegant pour over, glass flask that was invented in 1941 by Dr. Peter Schlumbohm. It uses a special Chemex paper filter that is 20-30% heavier than other filters. Similar to the coffee cone, hot water is poured over coffee grounds in a paper filter. The brewed coffee drips into the bottom of the flask which doubles as its own carafe.</p>
<ul>
<li>Grind of Beans: medium-coarse</li>
<li>Ground Coffee: 6 tablespoons of coffee (42g)</li>
<li>Brewing Time: 4 minutes</li>
<li>Flavour Profile: balanced, cleaner, refined, floral, sweet notes and non-acidic</li>
<li>Cost: $45-78 (extra cost for filters)</li>
<li>Different sizes yields up to 6 cups</li>
<li>Harder to clean and requires special brush</li>
<li>Portable but fragile</li>
<li>Requires Chemex paper filters</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Plunger/Press: French Press</strong></h3>
<p>The French Press method, invented in 1929, is widely considered as the best and easiest method for brewing superior and consistent coffee. It extracts, arguably, more superior flavours than any other method. In a press pot, ground coffee is soaked, steeped and strained in hot water; therefore, coffee’s flavourful essential oils, caffeine and antioxidants are better diffused and preserved leaving the purest flavours of the coffee. It is well suited for coffee drinkers that enjoy a luscious, expressive and complex taste experience.  </p>
<ul>
<li>Grind of Beans: coarse</li>
<li>Ground Coffee: 2-2.5 tablespoons of coffee (14-17g) for one cup</li>
<li>Brewing Time: 4 minutes</li>
<li>Flavour Profile: pure, clean flavour nuances that are complex and robust body</li>
<li>Cost: $8-112</li>
<li>Various sizes producing up to 8 cups of coffee</li>
<li>Easy to clean</li>
<li>Portable, especially the stainless steel thermal variety</li>
<li>No filters required</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Plunger/Press: AeroPress</strong></h3>
<p>Relatively new, the maker of Aerobie Frisbee (Alan Adler) created and launched the AeroPress in 2005. The AeroPress is plastic and comes in 3 parts. A filter sits in a coffee basket at the bottom of the brew chamber. Coffee grounds rest in the brew chamber where hot water is added then immerses/steeps the coffee. To extract the coffee, a plunger is pressed down creating air pressure to force brewed coffee through a filter and into a cup.</p>
<ul>
<li>Grind of Beans: fine-medium</li>
<li>Ground Coffee: 2.5 tablespoons of coffee (17g)</li>
<li>Brewing Time: 1-2 minutes</li>
<li>Flavour Profile: sweet, full-bodied, espresso-style coffee</li>
<li>Cost: $40-50 (extra cost for filters)</li>
<li>Produces a single cup of coffee</li>
<li>Easy to clean</li>
<li>Portable, especially popular with campers</li>
<li>Requires AeroPress micro paper filters (or a fine metal filter)</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Percolate: Stovetop Moka Pot</strong></h3>
<p>Originally patented in 1933 by Alfonso Bialetti, stovetop style coffee makers use steam pressure from boiled water in the lower section to pass through coffee grounds in the mid chamber of the pot. Brewed coffee then sits in the higher chamber. A well designed stovetop pot will created better pressure. Common brands include Bialetti, Pedrini, and Kabalo.</p>
<ul>
<li>Grind of Beans: Fine-Medium Coarse</li>
<li>Ground Coffee: 2.5-3 tablespoons of coffee (17-22g)</li>
<li>Brewing Time: 5 minutes</li>
<li>Flavour Profile: espresso-style coffee, strong and can be bitter</li>
<li>Cost: $20-60</li>
<li>Requires a gas stove</li>
<li>Produces the equivalent of a single or double shot</li>
<li>Easy to clean</li>
<li>Portable and durable</li>
<li>No extra filters required</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Vacuum: Siphon</strong></h3>
<p>The siphon is a fancy and flashy coffee maker. It can be a fun way to make coffee and impress friends at the same time, but it can be a fussy process. It was invented in Germany in the 1840s. Coffee grounds are added to the upper vessel and vapor pressure forces hot water up to immerse the coffee. Once the heat is removed, gravity pushes the brewed coffee back through a filter into the bottom vessel. Common brands include Hario, Yama and Bodum.</p>
<ul>
<li>Grind of Beans: Medium coarseness</li>
<li>Ground Coffee: 6 tablespoons of coffee (40g)</li>
<li>Brewing Time: 6 minutes</li>
<li>Flavour Profile: mellow and delicate flavours</li>
<li>Cost: $70-160 (extra cost for filters)</li>
<li>Produces several cups of coffee</li>
<li>Finicky to clean</li>
<li>Delicate and hard to store. Not portable.</li>
<li>Requires candle or butane burner (unless it has an electric heater), metal or cloth filter</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Additional Tips to improve home brewing methods:</strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Before use, rinse filters with hot water to remove any chemicals on the paper. Most common sized filters are also available unbleached.</li>
<li>For the pour over methods, employ a slow and steady pour of hot water in a spiral motion from the center outwards to thoroughly saturate all the coffee grounds evenly, which ensures optimal extraction.</li>
<li>To achieve even water distribution for the pour over and pressed coffee making methods, use a narrow spouted pouring kettle.</li>
<li>Start with cold, filtered water when possible.</li>
<li>Use fresh roasted beans and grind the beans just before brewing</li>
<li>Hot water should be just off boil (205F or 96C).</li>
<li>Rinse the makers and cups with hot water in advance to keep coffee hot for longer.</li>
<li>Some trial and error is to be expected when experimenting with new brew methods. Everyone’s taste preference varies, so don’t be afraid to adjust the grind or amount of coffee to suit your palette.</li>
<li>Don’t forget to compost your used coffee grinds, filters included!</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</article>
<nav class="navigation post-navigation" role="navigation" aria-label="Posts">
<div class="nav-links"> </div>
</nav>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> Everyone Suddenly Drinking Aloe Juice?</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/everyone-suddenly-drinking-aloe-juice.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/everyone-suddenly-drinking-aloe-juice.html</id>

        <updated>2023-05-29T16:30:01-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    We've heard beauty and wellness experts say that a green juice a day keeps aging skin away, but a new trend takes it to another level: drinking aloe juice. Not the gooey gel savior of sunburns, but a clear, slightly sour juice derived from the aloe&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <header class="css-joveom exadjwu10">
<div class="css-1lr08az e12wtocy0">
<div class="css-mktybr exadjwu2"> </div>
</div>
</header>
<div class="css-k008qs ewisyje0">
<div class="standard-container content-container article-container css-7ce51e ewisyje3">
<div class="content-lead css-trzem2 ewisyje6">
<div class="content-lead-image css-sm2oir e5f9kgu2"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">We've heard beauty and wellness experts say that a </span>green juice<span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> a day keeps aging skin away, but a new trend takes it to another level: drinking aloe juice. Not the gooey gel savior of sunburns, but a clear, slightly sour juice derived from the aloe plant (sounds appetizing, right?). Everyone from Goop founder (and pied piper of strange beauty rituals) Gwyneth Paltrow to naturopathic doctors are talking about its skin-improving benefits.</span></div>
</div>
<div class="article-body-content article-body standard-body-content css-z6i669 ewisyje7">
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0" data-node-id="4">Though no one juice—or food, for that matter—can single-handedly change your skin, there may be some sound scientific basis for the juice's newfound following. It's packed with vitamins, including B, C, and E, as well as folic acid, which fortify the body's immune system, the health of which is often reflected in the skin, says Wendy Bazilian, DrPH, RD, and author of <em>The SuperFoodsRx Diet</em>.</p>
<div class="journey-unblur-content css-0 e10xr3vp6" data-node-id="5" data-interactive="WatchNext-1" data-hydrated="">
<div class="css-1ujafpv e10xr3vp5" data-embed="watch-next">
<div class="css-lnz2n e10xr3vp4">
<div class="css-v78gcm e10xr3vp3">
<h6 class="css-vhh48g e10xr3vp0"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">"If you have a tendency toward dry skin or other skin issues including psoriasis, you can help promote healing from the inside out by choosing foods that are anti-inflammatory, like aloe juice," she says. Plus, it's also rich in antioxidants, which help protect cells against skin-damaging free radicals in the environment (think sun, smog, and other pollutants your skin is battling on a daily basis).</span></h6>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0" data-node-id="11">But before you chug a gallon of the stuff, know this: Though its nutritional stats are impressive, there isn't any research backing the claim that aloe juice can improve the look of your skin.</p>
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0" data-node-id="13">"It probably doesn't directly affect your skin, but anything that improves your overall health could potentially improve your appearance," says Rebecca Kazin, MD, of the Washington Institute of Dermatologic Laser Surgery. However, stay off the juice if you're taking medications for digestive issues, a blood disorder, or diabetes, as aloe can have mild laxative and blood-thinning effects, and can cause a drop in blood sugar in diabetics with already low levels.</p>
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0" data-node-id="15">If you're intrigued and want to test-drive the beauty elixir yourself, Bazilian suggests finding an organic, high-quality, filtered version of the juice (also known as aloe water), free of any additives like flavorings or sugars.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Best Herbs And Spices For Brain Health</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/best-herbs-and-spices-for-brain-health.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/best-herbs-and-spices-for-brain-health.html</id>

        <updated>2023-05-29T16:27:05-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Herbs and spices are the saving grace of many a strict diet plan. Constantly saluted for their calorie-free, fat-free, junk-free flavor additions, those dashes and pinches make the difference between legitimately enjoying clean eating and suffering through another baked chicken breast. But herbs and spices aren't&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <header class="css-joveom exadjwu10">
<div class="css-1lr08az e12wtocy0">
<div class="css-mktybr exadjwu2">
<div class="no-print css-wkpw2c exadjwu13">
<div class="content-header-actions css-1hpjtwr exadjwu12"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Herbs and spices are the saving grace of many a strict diet plan. Constantly saluted for their calorie-free, fat-free, junk-free flavor additions, those dashes and pinches make the difference between legitimately enjoying </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/food/healthy-eating-tips/23-ways-eat-clean" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/food/healthy-eating-tips/23-ways-eat-clean" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="clean eating" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">clean eating</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> and suffering through another baked chicken breast.</span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</header>
<div class="listicle-container content-container listicle-body-content css-4rmlxi erx0a9f17">
<section class="css-t6ry6e erx0a9f16">
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<div class="css-tmj2mr e1tmud0h5">
<div class="css-7oiw1p e1tmud0h6">
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0">But herbs and spices aren't only winners for your waistline. A handful also have promising research behind them suggesting big benefits for your brain, like a <a href="http://www.prevention.com/health/healthy-living/wine-and-chocolate-shown-improve-memory" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/health/healthy-living/wine-and-chocolate-shown-improve-memory" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="sharper memory" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0">sharper memory</a>, less anxiety, and maybe even protection from brain tumors. Here are a few it can't hurt to add to your favorite recipes.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<h2 class="css-1nrz9wd e1tmud0h7">Parsley and Thyme</h2>
<a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4"></a>
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A </span></a><a href="http://www.regenerativebiology.net/index.php/arb/article/view/29244" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.regenerativebiology.net/index.php/arb/article/view/29244" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="recent study" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">recent study</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> from Brazil found that a flavonoid in these spices, called apigenin, strengthened connections between neurons and even coaxed stem cells—our "raw material" cells that can form other specialized ones—into becoming neurons. While these results were produced in a lab setting and not in living, breathing humans, the researchers hypothesize that a diet rich in apigenin might influence brain cell formation and communication, too, which, in theory, could help ward off </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/mind-body/emotional-health/are-you-bummed-outor-depressed" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/mind-body/emotional-health/are-you-bummed-outor-depressed" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="depression" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">depression</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">, Alzheimer's, and </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/health/health-concerns/exercise-shown-significantly-lower-parkinsons-risk" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/health/health-concerns/exercise-shown-significantly-lower-parkinsons-risk" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="Parkinson's" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Parkinson's</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">. </span></div>
<div class="css-tmj2mr e1tmud0h5">
<div class="css-7oiw1p e1tmud0h6">
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0">Apigenin's chemical structure is similar to that of estrogen, explains Giana Angelo, PhD, a research associate at the Micronutrient Information Center at Oregon State University's Linus Pauling Institute, who was not involved in the research. Estrogen's long been known to influence neuron development, she says. "In this study, apigenin was able to mimic estrogen and elicit the same types of cellular changes."</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<h2 class="css-1nrz9wd e1tmud0h7">Chamomile</h2>
<a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4"></a>
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A perennial favorite of late-night tea drinkers, chamomile is, at least anecdotally, a tried-and-true stress destroyer.</span></a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> Like with apigenin, we've only got lab studies to go on when we think about how chamomile works its herbal magic on the brain, but it contains compounds that might bind to receptors for certain brain chemicals, reducing anxiety in the process, Angelo explains. In one </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19593179" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19593179" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="study" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">study</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">—in actual humans!—a small group of people with generalized anxiety disorder were randomized to either take a chamomile extract or a placebo. Eight weeks later, the people who had been taking chamomile reported a bigger drop in their anxiety.</span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<div> </div>
<section class="css-t6ry6e erx0a9f16">
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<h2 class="css-1nrz9wd e1tmud0h7">Turmeric</h2>
<a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4">
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Bear with us for some important-to-understand background: We've all got these immune cells called macrophages that destroy foreign particles, Angelo explains, but in some patients with Alzheimer's, macrophages can't do their jobs as well. With subpar macrophage-ing, the buildup of beta-amyloid plaques thought to contribute to the disease can't be swept away. Certain compounds found in turmeric (read up all about </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/health/turmeric-healing-benefits?cid=isynd_EC_0116" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/health/turmeric-healing-benefits?cid=isynd_EC_0116" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="the superspice here" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">the superspice here</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">) have been shown to kick-start those macrophages, she says, potentially helping to clear the plaques from the brains of people with </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17652175" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17652175" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="early signs of Alzheimer's" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">early signs of Alzheimer's</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">. What's still to be determined is how the high dose of these isolated compounds applied in petri dishes translates to how much curry you'd need to eat regularly to really make an impact, she cautions.</span></div>
</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<h2 class="css-1nrz9wd e1tmud0h7">Sage</h2>
<a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4">
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Aptly named for the cause, sage seems to </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/tags/memory-loss" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/tags/memory-loss" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="improve memory" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">improve memory</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">. In two small </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12895685" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12895685" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="studies" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">studies</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">, capsules of sage extract improved people's performance on memory tests, compared with placebo—for hours after </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18350281" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18350281" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="popping the pill" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">popping the pill</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">. "Other studies in animals indicate that essential oils and extracts of sage block the activity of an enzyme that degrades a neurotransmitter involved in many brain functions," Angelo says, "including learning, memory, and attention." In other words, sage might bolster that all-important enzyme. Be cautious when considering sage supplements, though, she says, as they can be dangerous for some people, including those with high blood pressure, since sage might make BP even higher.</span></div>
</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<h2 class="css-1nrz9wd e1tmud0h7">Garlic</h2>
<a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4">
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">It would be truly miraculous if the cure for a deadly brain tumor was simply to eat more garlic, as some headlines seemed to suggest back when 2007 </span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17647244" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17647244" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="research" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">research</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> was making waves. What the study actually showed about garlic was that certain active compounds in the odoriferous bulb can kill cancer cells—grown in a petri dish. "We can't make the leap from this study to what ingestion of garlic will actually do in a real live human brain," Angelo warns, especially because the researchers used much higher amounts of those specific garlic compounds than would be found in an actual clove, but it's certainly a promising start.</span></div>
</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<div class="css-1y4quq0 e1tmud0h0"> </div>
</section>
<div> </div>
<section class="css-t6ry6e erx0a9f16">
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8">
<h2 class="css-1nrz9wd e1tmud0h7">Peppermint</h2>
<a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4">
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A common cure for nausea, </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/food/healthy-recipes/5-steps-better-tea" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/food/healthy-recipes/5-steps-better-tea" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="peppermint tea" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">peppermint tea</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> has also been found to improve long-term and working memory in healthy adults, </span><a href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2016-04/bps-ptc042816.php" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2016-04/bps-ptc042816.php" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="according to research" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">according to research</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> presented at the British Psychological Society's Annual Conference. The study examined 180 participants who were split into three groups and given peppermint tea, chamomile tea, or hot water. Twenty minutes later, the participants had their memory and cognitive functions tested, </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/food/6-clean-foods-to-beat-depression" target="_self" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/food/6-clean-foods-to-beat-depression" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="as well as their moods" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">as well as their moods</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">. Researchers found that peppermint tea drastically improved long-term memory, working memory, and alertness, compared with hot water and chamomile tea (which actually slowed memory and attention speed).</span></div>
</a>
<div class="css-tmj2mr e1tmud0h5">
<div class="css-7oiw1p e1tmud0h6">
<p class="css-18vfmjb et3p2gv0"><span style="color: var(--headings-color); font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; font-weight: var(--font-weight-bold); letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">Rosemary</span></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section class="css-1igyocc e1tmud0h10">
<div class="css-q242xx e1tmud0h9">
<div class="listicle-slides css-ducv57 eemzdg80">
<div class="css-189pu4y e1tmud0h8"><a class="css-w84tga epl65fo4">
<div class="css-823ugw ew0wum60"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">This spice drawer staple can also be used to improve your memory. </span><a href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2016-04/bps-rac042716.php" target="_blank" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2016-04/bps-rac042716.php" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="More research" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" rel="noopener" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">More research</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);"> presented at the British Psychological Society's Annual Conference shows that the smell of rosemary essential oil can improve the prospective memory of those over 65. Prospective memory is the ability to remember specific events and tasks that will happen in the future—like your 2 PM appointment or partner's birthday. The study examined 150 people over 65, and divided them into three groups: one group was put in a lavender-scented room, another in a rosemary-scented room, and the last, a room with no scent at all. Researchers found that those sniffing rosemary experienced enhanced prospective </span><a href="http://www.prevention.com/health/test-your-memory-at-home" data-vars-ga-outbound-link="http://www.prevention.com/health/test-your-memory-at-home" data-vars-ga-ux-element="Hyperlink" data-vars-ga-call-to-action="memory" class="body-link css-7l5upj et3p2gv0" style="font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">memory</a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">, along with increased alertness, compared with those in the lavender and unscented rooms.</span></div>
</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
</section>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> Herbs Proven to Reduce Stress</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/herbs-proven-to-reduce-stress.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/herbs-proven-to-reduce-stress.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/17/pulling-out-hair-520x330-830035039.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="tea"/>

        <updated>2023-05-27T11:41:14-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/17/pulling-out-hair-520x330-830035039.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Do you want to find natural stress remedies that work for you? Here are four herbs to reduce stress levels at home and work. As you no doubt know all too well, we live in a chronically stressed culture. Most of us exist in a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/17/pulling-out-hair-520x330-830035039.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Do you want to find natural stress remedies that work for you? Here are four herbs to reduce stress levels at home and work.</p>
<p>As you no doubt know all too well, we live in a chronically stressed culture. Most of us exist in a state of near-constant overwork and overwhelm.</p>
<p>And all this stress is taking a serious toll. An estimated 90% of all visits to primary care doctors are for stress-related complaints.</p>
<p>Some stress can help you, by driving you to heightened alertness or intensity of focus. But <strong>too much</strong> <strong>stress can cause serious damage to your health</strong> — from contributing to weight gain to damaging your heart and making you look older. Stress can also affect how you feel physically and mentally.</p>
<p>Plus, <strong>chronic, or lasting, stress is linked to every chronic disease</strong> because it lays the foundation for inflammation and other health ailments.</p>
<p>You can’t avoid all the stress in your life. So, what’s the solution? How can you cope and not let all the little things, or the big ones, get you down?</p>
<p>You have more power over your stress than you may realize. Life isn’t only about what happens to you — it’s also about how you respond. The right herbs can be a potent tool to help you calm the stresses and enjoy more resiliency.</p>
<h2>Why Herbs Can Be An Easy and Effective Solution to Fight Stress</h2>
<p>An herb is a plant with leaves, seeds, or flowers that people use for flavoring, food, medicine, or perfume. In the modern world, people use the word “herb” to refer to a plant that’s used for healing or medicinal purposes.</p>
<p>For centuries, people in many cultures around the world have used a variety of herbs to fight stress. And, as you’ll see below, science is beginning to prove the remarkable powers of some of these plants.</p>
<h2>How Adaptogens Can Give You Calm and Clarity</h2>
<p>Adaptogens promote balance in many systems of your body. Remarkably, they can <strong>calm you down and boost your energy at the same time, without over-stimulating you</strong>.</p>
<p>While some adaptogens work quickly, most work over time and have cumulative benefits. Some people take them daily for months before getting the full effects.</p>
<h2>Ashwagandha — An Adaptogenic Herb Proven to Ease Stress and Energize Your Body</h2>
<p>Used in Ayurvedic medicine for over 2,500 years, ashwagandha is also known as winter cherry and Indian ginseng.</p>
<p>People often use this herb to help balance fatigue, exhaustion, stress, depression, and nervous tension.</p>
<p>In addition, it has the power to lower inflammation and fight infection.</p>
<h3>What Science Says About Ashwagandha</h3>
<p>Research is now proving the abilities of ashwagandha to ease anxiety and reduce feelings of stress.</p>
<p>In a 2012 study published in the Indian Journal of Psychological Medicine, patients were given 300 mg of ashwagandha root extract twice a day for 60 days. What happened? The participant’s scores of <strong>perceived stress dropped by 44% and their levels of the stress hormone cortisol (which goes up when stress levels are high) decreased by almost 28%.</strong></p>
<p>Then, in 2014, a systematic review of five controlled studies involving humans found that this herb <strong>significantly improved anxiety and stress levels.</strong></p>
<h3>How to Use Ashwagandha in Your Life</h3>
<p>If you’re feeling fatigued or burned out or like you need to relax and get some sleep, ashwagandha may be able to help.</p>
<p>Finding products made with ashwagandha root is typically best.</p>
<p>Some ways to use this herb:</p>
<ul>
<li>Made into tea</li>
<li>As a capsule or tablet</li>
<li>In a liquid extract or tincture</li>
<li>As a powder, which you can add to foods and beverages</li>
</ul>
<p>People have used ashwagandha traditionally in India in a powder mixed with warm milk, taken about an hour before bed. Ashwagandha is also often added to golden milk recipes made with turmeric. You can make plant-based versions of golden milk with unsweetened non-dairy milk and ashwagandha powder.</p>
<p>While taking ashwagandha is considered safe for most people, some health professionals advise against taking it if you’re pregnant or breastfeeding.</p>
<h2>Tulsi, or Holy Basil — An Adaptogen Herb You Can Take Daily to Help Your Body Respond to Stress</h2>
<p>Tulsi, also known as holy basil or “the queen of herbs,” is commonly used in Ayurvedic medicine, and is a member of the mint family.</p>
<p>This plant is a powerful antioxidant. While people have used it for a variety of treatments, <strong>it’s most significant potential might be for stress-relief and relaxation</strong>.</p>
<p>People who take it often report that it gives them a calming energy and a general sense of well-being.</p>
<p>Tulsi has also been found to help regulate your blood sugar and support heart health.</p>
<p>In traditional healing systems, people have often taken this herb over a lifetime to increase vibrant health and longevity.</p>
<h3>What Science Says About Tulsi</h3>
<p>In a 2012 randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study published in the international, peer-reviewed journal Evidence-Based Complementary and Alternative Medicine, 158 highly stressed individuals received either a placebo or holy basil.</p>
<p>After six weeks, <strong>the holy basil group reported improved symptoms of general stress 39% more than the placebo group</strong>.</p>
<p>Symptoms, such as frequent feelings of exhaustion, forgetfulness, and sleep problems decreased significantly. And participants reported no adverse effects.</p>
<p>Another 2008 study published in the Nepal Medical College Journal involved patients with generalized anxiety disorder. Researchers found that 500 mg of holy basil twice daily <strong>significantly reduced anxiety and associated stress, depression, and inattention </strong>in participants.</p>
<p>Further evidence is mounting that tulsi can address physical, chemical, metabolic, and psychological stress. It has been found to protect organs and tissues against chemical stress from industrial pollutants and heavy metals and against physical stress from prolonged physical exertion and exposure to cold and excessive noise.</p>
<p>The University of Maryland Medical Center recommends <strong>tulsi for people who have post-traumatic stress disorder, or PTSD</strong>. Getting specific, the Center recommends 400 milligrams of tulsi daily to help fight stress and to support adrenal health.</p>
<h3>How to Use Tulsi in Your Life</h3>
<p>Use tulsi regularly to help balance your body and support its response to everyday stressors.</p>
<p>Some ways to use this herb:</p>
<ul>
<li>As a tea (I particularly love Organic India tulsi products)</li>
<li>In cooking</li>
<li>As a capsule or tablet</li>
<li>In a powder form</li>
</ul>
<p>According to herbalist Rosalee De La Foret, tulsi may have an antifertility effect. Therefore, pregnant women or couples who want to conceive shouldn’t take this herb.</p>
<h2>How Nervine Herbs Support Your Nervous System</h2>
<p>Most nervine herbs are gentle and support relaxation. (By contrast, a few nervine herbs, such as coffee and peppermint, have stimulating qualities.)</p>
<p>Relaxing nervine herbs support the nervous system and reduce overactive stress responses by returning the body to a resting phase.</p>
<p>These herbs may be helpful for a variety of problems, such as relieving normal muscle tension, wakeful nights, and occasional worries.</p>
<h2>Lemon Balm — A Nervine Herb with Powerful Relaxing and Mood-Boosting Benefits</h2>
<p>A member of the mint family, lemon balm has been studied for its anti-anxiety effects. For thousands of years, people have used it medicinally. And today, it’s often combined with other calming herbs, such as chamomile, valerian, and lavender.</p>
<p>With its citrusy notes, the scent and the delightful taste make it an enjoyable way to soothe and boost your mood.</p>
<h3>What Science Says About Lemon Balm</h3>
<p>Randomized, double-blind research published in 2004 in the journal Psychosomatic Medicine gave participants a single dose of lemon balm (300 mg or 600 mg) or a placebo. After an hour, those taking the higher dose reported <strong>reduced stress and improved calmness and alertness</strong>.</p>
<p>In another 2011 study, 20 adults with moderate anxiety and insomnia were given 300 mg of lemon balm twice per day for 15 days. Researchers found the lemon balm <strong>reduced anxiety and related symptoms by as much as 18% and decreased insomnia by 42%.</strong> And they observed no adverse effects.</p>
<p>Lemon balm is also able to effectively increase GABA activity in the brain. Your brain uses the neurotransmitter GABA to<strong> prevent over-excitement and achieve balance</strong>. It helps keeps our stress levels low and plays a role in sleep.</p>
<h3>How to Use Lemon Balm in Your Life</h3>
<p>For most people, lemon balm is considered safe to take daily. Some health practitioners even recommend using it to soothe teething children. Many people use it to improve their mood and stress levels, as well as for anxiety or seasonal affective disorder.</p>
<p>Some ways to use this herb:</p>
<ul>
<li>As a tea</li>
<li>In tinctures or syrups</li>
<li>In cooking and baking</li>
<li>Lemon-balm infused water</li>
</ul>
<p>If you have leaves from this plant, you can simply rub a leaf between your fingers to absorb some of its essential oils aromatically. Fresh lemon balm has its own special benefits, and it’s easy to grow in containers.</p>
<h2>Curcumin — An Herb Component That Can Boost Your Mood and Help Offset the Impact Stress Has on Your Body</h2>
<p>Curcumin is the most active compound in the turmeric root. You’ve probably heard about the vast range of health benefits curcumin and turmeric can provide. In fact, here are 600 reasons turmeric may be the world’s most important herb.</p>
<p>But you may not be aware that this magical herb can <strong>help relieve stress and anxiety</strong>.</p>
<h3>What Science Says About Curcumin</h3>
<p>Amazingly, curcumin has been found to reverse harmful brain changes induced by chronic stress.</p>
<p>Human studies are also showing its potential to fight stress. A 2016 study published in the Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology showed that taking 500 mg of curcumin twice daily, with fenugreek, considerably <strong>reduced stress, anxiety, and fatigue while significantly increasing the quality of life in people suffering from extreme occupational stress</strong>.</p>
<p>In another 2015 study published in the Journal of Psychopharmacology, 400 mg of curcumin was given to healthy adults aged 60 to 85. Only one hour after a single dose, participants scored better on tasks requiring sustained attention and working memory. Continuous use for weeks <strong>improved scores on working memory and mood, including general fatigue, calmness, and contentedness</strong>.</p>
<p>And it can even help with PMS. In a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study published in 2016 in Neuropeptides, Curcumin was found to <strong>reduce anxiety experienced by women with PMS</strong> and to significantly reduce PMS-related emotional, behavioral, and physical symptoms.</p>
<h3>How to Use Curcumin in Your Life</h3>
<p>Curcumin is generally considered safe to take indefinitely. But unfortunately, the body isn’t able to absorb it and make use of its benefits very efficiently.</p>
<p>Some people eat turmeric with black pepper and a fat source, such as ghee or coconut oil, as has been done traditionally in India for many centuries to boost bioavailability. But many people find it easiest to achieve optimal levels with curcumin supplementation.</p>
<p>At FRN, we recommend making use of a micelle liposomal delivery mechanism because it’s been found to increase bioavailability by up to 185 times.</p>
<p>Purality Health offers a premium organic liposomal curcumin, combined with a number of other potent anti-inflammatories to create a product they call Curcumin Gold. </p>
<h2>Important Considerations About Herbs</h2>
<p>Herbs can be surprisingly useful in helping you to reduce your stress at home and at work. But you can’t use herbs to singlehandedly make up for a lack of sleep, poor diet, lack of exercise, or being stuck in toxic relationships.</p>
<p>So, if you’re experiencing negative effects of stress, it’s important to consider not only how to recover but also what you can do to best minimize the factors that are causing you stress.</p>
<p>In herbal medicine, herbalists often use multiple herbs in combination with each other to achieve greater effects. You can find tea blends to reduce your stress, or you can make your own.</p>
<h2>A Final Word About Using Herbs to Reduce Stress</h2>
<p>Take time to find natural stress remedies that work for you and that are backed by science. You’ll be taking action to help your body, mind, and spirit feel calmer and better able to respond to the inevitable challenges life brings.</p>
<p>Knowing how to use the right herbs can make a very real difference in your quality, and even quantity, of life.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Specialty vs Commercial Coffee Processing Differences</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/specialty-vs-commercial-coffee-processing-differences.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/specialty-vs-commercial-coffee-processing-differences.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/16/2315310261_8db6825857-797451361.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="tea"/>
            <category term="coffee"/>

        <updated>2023-05-27T11:40:07-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/16/2315310261_8db6825857-797451361.jpeg" alt="" />
                    What is it that makes specialty coffee so special? We know it’s much better quality than commercial-grade beans, but why? Is it picked off the tree, already loaded with those unique and flavorful characteristics we love? If only it were that easy! There’s a significant&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/16/2315310261_8db6825857-797451361.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">What is it that makes specialty coffee so special? We know it’s much better quality than commercial-grade beans, but why? Is it picked off the tree, already loaded with those unique and flavorful characteristics we love?  </span></p>
<div class="single-content">
<p>If only it were that easy!</p>
<p>There’s a significant amount of detailed work that goes into producing a high-quality micro-lot specialty coffee. Everything from fertilizers to the amount of shade, and from the altitude to the variety of crops that are planted within the micro-lots have an effect on the quality of the coffee.  But the effort doesn’t stop once you’ve decided what to plant where and with what. To produce a specialty bean, the attention to detail must continue throughout the <i>entire </i>process – and there are three quality control points that can really make a difference to the final cup.  </p>
<br>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><strong style="font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">1. THE CHERRY PICKERS: </strong><strong style="font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">GO REDS!</strong></figure>
</div>
<p>Think cherry picking is basic work? Think again. The first line of quality control begins in the fields with these hardworking people.</p>
<p>Traditionally, coffee pickers were instructed to pick any and all cherries in sight – green, yellow, red, or even black. Yes, black. It was quantity over quality, since coffee has typically been sold as a basic commodity rather than a luxury product. With a business model like that, the more there is, the more money you get.</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Yet with third wave coffee, things are changing. Pickers on specialty coffee farms are taught to pick </span><i style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">only </i><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">the red, ripe cherries. This is extremely important, as an underdeveloped or overdeveloped cherry can give the final cup a sour or bitter taste. It’s a difficult transition for a farm to make, as pickers are typically paid by the weight of the cherries they’ve picked. On specialty coffee farms, pickers are still compensated based on weight </span><i style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">but </i><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">they are paid premiums to make up for the fact that the weight picked is less and the work is more tedious.  </span></figure>
</div>
<p>Nobody is perfect, though, and so occasionally over- or underdeveloped cherries do fall into the sacks.  So some farms take it a step further and do a hand-selection process of the red cherries that are picked throughout the day to weed out any of the stragglers that get through.  This ensures that only the best and ripest cherries make it through to the wet mill.</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><strong style="font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">2. PARCHMENT COFFEE: HUNT OUT THOSE DEFECTS!</strong></figure>
</div>
<p>After the cherries have been run through the wet mill and dried to the optimal humidity level, it’s time for the next stage: the hulling. And this is where the second quality control check is.</p>
<p>Why so many quality control checks? Well, even the ripest, reddest of cherries can hide defects. They may look great to the naked eye, there’s no telling what lies underneath that pulp…</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><figure class="wp-image-5528"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://perfectdailygrind.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC00913-min-1024x768.jpg" alt="Sorting coffee" width="1000" data-is-external-image="true"></figure></figure>
</div>
<p>Parchment beans with visible defects are hand-selected and then tossed into a pile of <i>pasilla.</i> <i>Pasilla</i> is the defective beans which, unfortunately, will still be sold in the market.  It’s what you would typically find in commercial grade coffee and is what most Colombians drink on a daily basis.</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><strong style="font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">3. GREEN BEANS: THE FINAL STAGE</strong></figure>
</div>
<p>Once the beans have been hulled, they’re left in their final stage prior to roasting: green. And yet again, a quality control check is needed. The parchment, just like the pulp, can hide defects. And per the SCAA criteria, specialty coffee must have zero primary defects, so it’s crucial to get rid of any defective beans.  </p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><figure class="wp-image-5523"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://perfectdailygrind.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC00329-min-1024x768.jpg" alt="Defective beans" width="1000" data-is-external-image="true"></figure></figure>
</div>
<p>This last quality control point has traditionally been done by hand, but there are now machines that can do the job. Hand-selecting is the ideal method because it provides employment to the local community.</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">However, it’s not always the most time-efficient – especially for large cooperatives handling a huge volume.  As a small exporter/importer handling small micro-lots, I focus on maintaining economic and social sustainability within the communities we work with and so prefer the traditional method of hand-sorting. Yet for others, a machine may be a more viable option.</span></figure>
</div>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><strong style="font-family: var(--font-base); font-size: 1.60181em; letter-spacing: var(--letter-spacing);">ROAST READY – BUT THE QUALITY CONTROL CONTINUES</strong></figure>
</div>
<p>By now, the process at farm-level is complete and the beans are ready to be roasted, free of defects and full of flavor. But if you think the quality checks stop here, you’re mistaken! The quality control points continue on until the final cup is served and enjoyed.</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><figure class="wp-image-5524"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://perfectdailygrind.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/DSC00335-min-1024x768.jpg" alt="Cupping at Colombian Coffee Federation" width="1000" data-is-external-image="true"></figure></figure>
</div>
<p>Of course, these three processing quality control checks that we’ve been talking about will ensure that the number of rejected beans is minimal.</p>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">By enforcing these three quality control points consistently and effectively during the processing stage, the quality of the coffee beans will noticeably improve. So next time you sit down with a delicious cup of specialty coffee, know it’s not just the beans themselves that make the coffee taste so great – it’s also the meticulous processes and hard work of those quality control checkers at origin.</span></figure>
</div>
<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter is-resized"><i style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">A lot of hard work goes into bringing the consumer these high-quality specialty coffee beans. Cupping session at the Colombian Coffee Federation.</i></figure>
</div>
<p>And thank god they do check!</p>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>How Coffee Became an Everyday Drink</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/how-coffee-became-an-everyday-drink.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/how-coffee-became-an-everyday-drink.html</id>
            <category term="coffee"/>

        <updated>2023-05-27T11:41:44-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    For many of us, drinking coffee is such a ubiquitous activity we hardly notice we’re doing it. But Steven Topik reminds us that in various times and places, the coffee bean has represented a spiritual practice, a political controversy, and even a form of money. The&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>For many of us, drinking coffee is such a ubiquitous activity we hardly notice we’re doing it. But Steven Topik reminds us that in various times and places, the coffee bean has represented a spiritual practice, a political controversy, and even a form of money.</p>
<p>The history of coffee starts in Ethiopia, where it grew wild. Topik writes that locals used it as a sacrament in communal ceremonies and to keep up energy and blunt hunger during hunting treks.</p>
<p>As the beans spread to other parts of Africa, some groups made the fresh coffee berries into drinks, while others roasted them in fat or butter, or simply chewed them up. They were light and valuable enough that the Haya people of Tanzania adopted coffee as currency, pricing livestock and other commodities in terms of coffee beans.</p>
<p>When coffee started to go global, it was thanks to Arabian traders. Sufi Muslims in Yemen particularly prized the drink, which became part of their nighttime chanting rituals.</p>
<aside class="pull-quote center">
<div class="pull-quote__text tweetable"> </div>
</aside>
<p>Yemeni coffee also had effects back in the material world. The nation became the dominant source of coffee for 250 years, influencing the economic and military fortunes of the Ottoman Empire.</p>
<p>Across Muslim nations, coffee was controversial. Topik writes that it held obvious appeal for people who avoided alcohol, particularly during late-night Ramadan celebrations. But some religious scholars objected, concerned about its medicinal properties and convinced by interpretations of the Koran that warned against its use.</p>
<p>Another concern was the rise of coffeehouses. Because coffee brewing demanded technical skill, merchants couldn’t just sell the beans to uninitiated customers, so they opened coffeehouses wherever they went. The new gathering places worried some religious leaders because of their challenge to mosques as central spaces for socializing and political discussion.</p>
<p>Still, by 1500, the drink was popular around the Arabian Peninsula. Some stories even credited Muhammad and the Archangel Gabriel for bringing the drink to the earth.</p>
<div class="daily_email_signup weekly-digest ">
<div id="wpcf7-f50708-p39677-o2" class="wpcf7" dir="ltr" lang="en-US"><form class="wpcf7-form init" action="https://daily.jstor.org/how-coffee-went-from-a-mystical-sacrament-to-an-everyday-drink/#wpcf7-f50708-p39677-o2" method="post" novalidate="novalidate" aria-label="Contact form" data-status="init">
<p class="email-additional"><a href="http://www.jstor.org/contact-us/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"></a><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Middle Easterners drank their coffee very dark and unsweetened, and when Europeans began encountering the drink they were generally unimpressed with the taste. But they attributed other attractive qualities to it, including medicinal properties and a general association with the wealth and luxury of the “Orient.”</span></p>
</form></div>
</div>
<p>Over time, Topik writes, those associations shifted. Coffee became a drink of European academics and emerging capitalists, an “anti-Bacchus” or “Great Soberer.”</p>
<p>But, just like in the Middle East, the social nature of coffeehouses worried some rulers. These concerns turned out to be justified when coffeehouses served as headquarters for the planning of revolutions in 1789 France and 1848 Berlin, Budapest, and Venice.</p>
<p>With the growth of consumer society in Europe and the U.S., coffee drinking spread to the working class. Where soldiers in the American Revolution had received rum rations, Civil War troops got coffee. One fighter claimed later that “if there had been reverence enough among the veterans to form the basis of a new religion, their gods would have been Fire and Coffee.”</p>
<p>Coffee drinking only got more common in the twentieth century as new inventions made it easy to brew coffee at home or in the office, turning it into the unremarkable daily activity it is today.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Milk vs Alternatives and How They Compare</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/milk-vs-alternatives-and-how-they-compare.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/milk-vs-alternatives-and-how-they-compare.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/14/th-3337197302.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Foods"/>

        <updated>2023-05-27T11:44:54-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/14/th-3337197302.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Instead of putting cow’s milk on their oatmeal in the morning, more and more people are switching to nondairy milk alternatives, such as soy, almond, and rice milk. Is this a bad thing? Americans are drinking far less cow’s milk than we used to, even&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/media/posts/14/th-3337197302.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Instead of putting cow’s milk on their oatmeal in the morning, more and more people are switching to nondairy milk alternatives, such as soy, almond, and rice milk.  Is this a bad thing? Americans are drinking far less cow’s milk than we used to, even though most people know that the calcium in milk helps to build strong bones.  Let’s compare the key nutrients in milk to those in popular milk alternatives.  We’ll also look at some key health benefits they have to offer.</p>
<p><span id="more-18"></span></p>
<h3>Calcium</h3>
<p>Milk is best known for being an excellent source of calcium, which helps build strong bones and prevent development of bone diseases like osteoporosis.  Calcium also plays a role in cell signaling, energy metabolism, blood pressure regulation, muscle contraction, and hormonal action.<sup>1</sup> Unfortunately, it turns out that we are unlikely to get enough calcium if we don’t eat or drink dairy.<sup>2</sup> A small (8 oz) glass of milk provides 20-30% of the recommended dietary allowance (RDA) for calcium for people over age 3. The good news is that milk alternatives like soy, rice, and almond milk are usually fortified with calcium so they provide the same amount as a glass of milk.<sup>3-4</sup> Be sure to look at the ingredient list though, since some types of calcium are more easily absorbed by the body – look for calcium carbonate instead of calcium triphosphate.<sup>5</sup></p>
<h3>Other Vitamins and Minerals</h3>
<p>Milk is a naturally good source of all kinds of nutrients besides just calcium, including potassium, phosphorus, riboflavin, and vitamin B12.<sup>3</sup> It also contains a fair amount of magnesium, thiamin, and zinc. Most milk and milk alternatives have added vitamin D, which aids in calcium absorption, as well as vitamin A. In fact, milk is a main dietary source of vitamin D for Americans.<sup>6  </sup>Many milk alternatives are also fortified with additional vitamins, such as vitamin B12, so that they more closely resemble the nutrient profile of milk.  If you check out the table below, which compares milk to milk alternatives, you’ll see that they are all pretty good. After fortifying soy milk with calcium, riboflavin, and vitamin B12, it’s a close tie between cow’s milk and soy milk. However, there’s more to the story.</p>
<h3>Protein</h3>
<p>Just like your mom always said, milk is an excellent source of protein.  One cup of milk contains more protein than a large egg!<sup>3</sup>  Proteins help your body do important things, like build and move muscles, catalyze chemical reactions, transport molecules, repair damage, and build protection. Not all proteins are created equal, though.  Your body breaks down the protein you eat into building blocks (called amino acids) that it needs to make proteins for specific purposes (like repairing a muscle). Some amino acids can only be obtained from the diet; these are called essential amino acids. The two types of protein in milk (whey and casein) are especially good because they are complete proteins, which means that they contain <em>all</em> of the essential amino acids in appropriate proportions.<sup>7-8</sup> Proteins also vary in how easy they are for your body to absorb and use, which we refer to as their biological value. Milk’s a winner here: whey protein (which makes up about 20% of milk protein) has the highest biological value of any protein source.<sup>8</sup> Of the common milk alternatives, soy milk is the only one that contains a comparable amount of protein. Soy protein is considered a complete, high quality vegetable protein, but it is lower in several essential amino acids compared to casein.<sup>9</sup></p>
<h3>Sugar and Carbohydrates</h3>
<p>Even though it’s not notably sweet, milk contains sugar.  The naturally-occurring sugar in milk is called lactose.  It can cause problems for some people whose bodies don’t make the enzyme to break it down.  Thankfully, lactose-free milk is widely available!  Lactose-free milk, oddly enough, tastes sweeter than regular milk because the lactose has been broken down into its component parts, glucose and galactose, and glucose is sweeter.  Milk alternatives are sometimes available unsweetened; unsweetened soy and almond milks are very low in sugar. However, most commercial brands have added sugar to improve taste. Look at the ingredients list to find out if sugar has been added. Remember that terms like “syrup” and “cane juice” in the ingredients list mean that there are added sugars. Milk alternatives that contain low or no added sugar may still contain carbohydrates if they are made from beans or grains or if they have added starch.  So, there’s no clear winner when it comes to sugar and carbohydrates, but check your labels!</p>
<h3><strong>Fat and</strong> Cholesterol</h3>
<p>Because cow’s milk comes from <span class="label label-warning">spoiler alert</span> <em>cows</em>, whole milk contains saturated fat and cholesterol. Low fat or fat free milk are recommended because they contain minimal amounts. Soy, rice, and almond milks are generally low in total and saturated fat and do not contain cholesterol because they are not derived from animals. Coconut milk, another popular milk alternative, generally contains a significant amount of saturated fat, even in light versions.<sup>3 </sup><strong> </strong></p>
<h3>Beyond Bone Health</h3>
<p>Milk and the major milk alternatives offer multiple health benefits, although some are better than others. Milk has been linked to decreased blood pressure, partly due to magnesium, potassium, calcium, and peptides derived from whey and casein proteins.<sup>7 </sup>It also contributes to reduced cardiovascular disease risk because of its high calcium content. Calcium intake is believed to promote heart health through effects on fat absorption and metabolism.<sup>1</sup> Soy milk may also be good for your heart, since some studies have shown a small decrease in LDL cholesterol with soy protein intake.<sup>10</sup> Here’s where you’ll really start paying attention, though: low fat and nonfat calcium-rich foods are believed to promote weight control due to effects of calcium on energy metabolism.<sup>11</sup> Soy milk and nonfat milk equally promoted weight loss in one study,<sup>12</sup> while milk had the greater effect on weight loss and waist circumference than soy milk in another study.<sup>13</sup> Because of the different types of protein they contain, milk is probably better than milk alternatives at suppressing appetite and food intake.<sup>14</sup></p>
<h3>How Much Milk Should You Drink?</h3>
<p>Two to three servings (cups) per day of milk, dairy, or milk alternatives are usually recommended.<sup>15</sup>  Don’t go too crazy, though, since there can indeed be too much of a good thing.  Very high intake of calcium could inhibit your body’s ability to absorb other nutrients like iron.Additionally, researchers are investigating whether there is a relationship between very high intakes of calcium, dairy, and soy and certain types of cancer.<sup>1,10</sup> Sticking to 2-3 servings per day will help you maximize the benefits of milk while minimizing any potential risks.</p>
<p>Also, despite being a healthy choice for kids and adults, milk and milk alternatives aren’t recommended for babies (babies need very specialized nutrition, so talk to your pediatrician about options for your infant).</p>
<p>So which milk comes out ahead? Based on our comparison, cow’s milk is still a front-runner for overall health benefits. If you have an allergy to milk, choose not to consume animal products, or simply prefer the taste, soy milk is also a great choice. While rice and almond milks are certainly healthier than many other beverage choices, their lower protein content makes them less ideal for most people.</p>
<p>Now, don’t you want to go drink a glass of milk?</p>
<table class="table table-striped" border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td colspan="5" valign="top" width="443"><strong>Nutrient Comparison of Milk and Milk Alternatives per 1 cup</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92"> </td>
<td valign="top" width="84">Cow’s milk, nonfat, with added vitamins A and D<sup>3</sup></td>
<td valign="top" width="91">Silk<sup>â</sup>soymilk, unsweetened, with added calcium, vitamins A, D, B12, and riboflavin<sup>3,16</sup></td>
<td valign="top" width="88">Rice milk, unsweetened, with added calcium and vitamins A and D<sup>3</sup></td>
<td valign="top" width="87">Almond Dream<sup>â</sup>almond milk, with added vitamins A, D, and B12<sup>4</sup></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Calories (kcal)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">83</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">80</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">113</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Protein (g)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">8.3</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">7</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">0.7</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Fat (g)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">0.2</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">4.0</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">2.3</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Sugars (g)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">12.5</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">1</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">12.7</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Calcium (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">299</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">299</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">283</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">300</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Riboflavin (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">0.5</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">0.5</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">0.3</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Vitamin D (IU)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">115</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">120</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">101</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">100</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Vitamin A (IU)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">500</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">501</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">499</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">1500</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Vitamin B12 (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">1.2</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">3.0</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">1.5</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Potassium (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">382</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">299</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">65</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Phosphorus (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">247</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">N/A</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">134</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Magnesium (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">27</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">39</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">26</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Zinc (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">1.0</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">0.6</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">0.3</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td valign="top" width="92">Cholesterol (mg)</td>
<td valign="top" width="84">5</td>
<td valign="top" width="91">0</td>
<td valign="top" width="88">0</td>
<td valign="top" width="87">0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td colspan="5" valign="top" width="443">N/A = information not available</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Nuts and Seeds in an Athlete&#x27;s Diet</title>
        <author>
            <name>jesse martin</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/nuts-and-seeds-in-an-athletes-diet.html"/>
        <id>https://tacocheesemac.github.io/gh-pages/nuts-and-seeds-in-an-athletes-diet.html</id>

        <updated>2023-05-24T12:57:52-07:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Times have changed from when we used to joke about folks who ate "nuts and berries"—the making's of a bland diet. Today's athletes routinely enjoy nuts and berries, and are now looking for ways to notch up their diets with more seeds—such as flax and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="article-header">
<h1 class="article-title"> </h1>
</div>
<div class="row article-content-wrapper">
<div id="column-center" class="span8">
<div class="sponsor-social-wrapper">
<div class="social-share social-share--top">
<div class="wrapper">
<div id="pinit-btn" class="social-share__icon social-share__icon--pinterest" data-type="pinterest" data-url="https://www.active.com/nutrition/articles/the-importance-of-nuts-and-seeds-in-an-athlete-s-diet" data-media="https://www.active.com/Assets/Nutrition/460/Nuts+$!26+Seeds+460.jpg" data-title="The Importance of Nuts and Seeds in an Athlete's Diet"><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">Times have changed from when we used to joke about folks who ate "nuts and berries"</span><span class="st" style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">—</span><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">the making's of a bland diet. Today's athletes routinely enjoy nuts and berries, and are now looking for ways to notch up their diets with more seeds</span><span class="st" style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">—</span><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">such as flax and chia</span><span class="st" style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">—</span><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">and whole grains like quinoa.</span></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<article id="article_content" class="section legacy">
<p>This trend can enhance the health of both our bodies and the planet. That is, by choosing more plant foods, we'll end up eating less meat and animal protein. If each of us were to eat just one less pound of beef per week, greenhouse gas emissions would drop significantly.</p>
<p>While seeds and grains are health-enhancing choices to include in your sports diet, their nutritional value can sometimes become exaggerated and mainstreamed.</p>
<h2>Nuts and Seeds</h2>
<p>Nuts and seeds offer protein, healthy fats, fiber, vitamin E, magnesium and many other nutrients. The fact that a plant grows from a nut or seed indicates it is life sustaining.</p>
<section class="section articles-featured-events activities-block"></section>
<p> </p>
<p>Many nuts and seeds offer alpha linoleic acid, also known as ALA, a type of health-protective omega-3 polyunsaturated fat. While ALA from plants is not as potent as the type of omega-3s found in fish, any omega-3 fat is better than none.</p>
<p>Want to add a nice crunch, along with vitamins and minerals, to your sports diet? Sprinkle some slivered almonds, chopped walnuts, pistachios, sunflower and sesame seeds into your yogurt, cereal salad or smoothie. </p>
<p>Despite all the benefits, dieters should be weary. When you nonchalantly toss a few spoonfuls of nuts and seeds into your smoothies and salads to pump up their nutritional value, you can also easily toss in 100 to 400 calories. While vegans may need this protein and calorie boost, weight-conscious athletes who consume dairy and animal proteins might want to think twice.</p>
<h2>Comparing Seeds and Nuts</h2>
<p>This chart shows how 1/4 cup of nuts and seeds<span class="st">—</span>two spoonfuls or a large handful<span class="st">—</span>adds a lot of calories but minimal protein towards the daily target of about 60 to 90 grams of protein. To get enough protein, vegans still need additional plant proteins, like beans or tofu.</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Seed</strong></p>
<div id="inarticle1" class="js-ad-placeholder show" data-position="inarticle1" data-ad-size="[[300, 250], &quot;fluid&quot;, [1, 1]]"></div>
<p>(1/4 cup, 30 g)</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Calories</strong></p>
<p> </p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Protein</strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Fiber</strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Calcium </strong></p>
<div id="inarticle2" class="js-ad-placeholder show" data-position="inarticle2" data-ad-size="[[300, 250], &quot;fluid&quot;, [1, 1]]"></div>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Iron </strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Chia</td>
<td align="center">140</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">180</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Flax, ground</td>
<td align="center">150</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">70</td>
<td align="center">1.5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Hemp</td>
<td align="center">180</td>
<td align="center">10</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">--</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Sunflower</td>
<td align="center">190</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">20</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Pumpkin</td>
<td align="center">170</td>
<td align="center">9</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">50</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Sesame</td>
<td align="center">200</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">350</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Walnuts</td>
<td align="center">190</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">30</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center"> </td>
<td align="center"> </td>
<td align="center">
<p>Daily Target:</p>
<p>60 to 90 grams</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p>Daily Target:</p>
<p>25 to 35 grams</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p>Daily Target:</p>
<p>1,000 mg</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p>Daily Target:</p>
<p>8 mg men</p>
<p>18 women</p>
</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Flax Seeds: </strong>Commonly consumed for their ALA omega-3 fat benefits, need to be ground before being eaten. Otherwise, they pass through your intestines whole and undigested.</p>
<p><strong>Chia Seeds:</strong> Also offer ALA omega-3 fats—but you don't need to grind them. Just sprinkle chia on yogurt and enjoy the crunch. When soaked in water for 10 minutes, chia seeds create a gel that can be used as a thickener for smoothies and as an alternative to eggs and oils in some recipes.</p>
<p>The slimy consistency of soaked chia seeds can be tough to enjoy for some athletes. If you fall into the "No, thank you" camp, worry not. You have many other options for enjoyably consuming similar nutrients in other seeds and nuts.</p>
<p><strong>Sunflower Seeds:</strong> A mild, pleasing taste when added to salads, trail mix or cold cereals. For people with peanut allergies, sunflower butter is a popular alternative to peanut butter.</p>
<p><strong>Pumpkin Seeds:</strong> Also known as pepitas, are slower to eat when you buy them in the shell. This can save unwanted calories.</p>
<p><strong>Hemp Seeds:</strong> Touted as containing all the essential amino acids. Hemp adds a protein-boost to vegan diets, but at a high price. Hemp seeds costs about $15 per pound, as compared to soy nuts, that also have all the amino acids, about $3.50/lb.</p>
<p><strong>Sesame Seeds: </strong>A gentle flavor and make a nice addition to stir-fried tofu or chicken. Although sesame seeds are touted as being calcium-rich, their calcium is poorly absorbed.</p>
<p><strong>Chopped Nuts: </strong>Such as walnuts or slivered almonds, add a protein boost—but not as much of a protein bonus as many athletes think. If you ate half a cup of walnuts (two man-sized handfuls), you'd get only eight grams of protein. For the same calories, you could add 1.5 cups of cottage cheese to your salad and get five times more protein (40 grams).</p>
<div id="inarticle1" class="js-ad-placeholder show" data-position="inarticle1" data-ad-size="[[300, 250], &quot;fluid&quot;, [1, 1]]"></div>
<h2>Grains</h2>
<p>Both whole and refined grain foods offer carbohydrates that easily fuel your muscles. Whole grains include whole wheat, brown rice, corn (including popcorn), oats, barley, millet, and quinoa. Unrefined grains offer trace minerals, such as magnesium and copper, that refined grains don't offer because they are lost in processing.</p>
<p>However, most refined grains are enriched with B-vitamins and iron, two important nutrients for athletes. So, if you end up eating some white pasta or bread, there's no need to fret! Dietary guidelines allow for half of the grains you consume to be refined.</p>
<p>Quinoa is actually a seed, but we eat it as a grain, and it offers more protein than other grains. But take note: Quinoa is not a protein powerhouse, so eat it with tofu, beans or yogurt to reach the target of 20 to 30 grams protein per meal. Quinoa is also expensive: $6 per pound, as compared to brown rice at $1.50 per pound.</p>
<p> </p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="center"><strong>Grain/Starch</strong></td>
<td align="center"><strong>One Cup Cooked<br></strong></td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Calories</strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Protein</strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
<div id="inarticle2" class="js-ad-placeholder show" data-position="inarticle2" data-ad-size="[[300, 250], &quot;fluid&quot;, [1, 1]]"></div>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Fiber</strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
<td align="center">
<p><strong>Iron</strong></p>
<p>(grams)</p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Pasta, white</td>
<td align="center">2 oz dry</td>
<td align="center">200</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Pasta, whole wheat</td>
<td align="center">2 oz dry</td>
<td align="center">200</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">6</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Rice, white</td>
<td align="center"> 1/3 cup raw</td>
<td align="center">225</td>
<td align="center">4</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Rice, brown</td>
<td align="center">1/3 cup raw</td>
<td align="center">225</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">2</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Couscous</td>
<td align="center">1/3 cup raw</td>
<td align="center">215</td>
<td align="center">7</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
<td align="center">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="center">Quinoa</td>
<td align="center">1/3 cup raw</td>
<td align="center">200</td>
<td align="center">8</td>
<td align="center">5</td>
<td align="center">3</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
<h2>The Bottom Line</h2>
<p>When you resolve to "eat healthier," be sure to create a sustainable plan that will offer lifelong enjoyment. While you want to explore new foods, you don't have to routinely choke down seeds and whole grains that do not really please your taste buds.</p>
<p>By filling your meals with a variety of wholesome foods—including generous portions of colorful fruits and vegetables—you'll be able to consume abundant nutrients that invest in both good health and top performance. Plus, you'll also help save the planet by choosing more seeds and grains and fewer steaks and chops.</p>
<p> </p>
</article>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
